{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "After they were slow in pledging their allegiance to this king, the MacDonald Clan were massacred in Glencoe. Upon taking the throne, this king was read the Declaration of Right by Parliament; that later became part of the English Bill of Rights. This King’s forces defeated James II’s Jacobite uprising at the Battle of the Boyne, after which this Dutch stadtholder assumed power in the Glorious Revolution. For ten points, name this husband of Mary II, a Prince of Orange and 17th century king of England.",
      "answer": "William III of England or William of Orange,"
    },
    {
      "question": "A precursor to this law known as the 15 Passenger Bill was resolved by Richard Angell after it was struck down by Rutherford Hayes. The Magnuson Act repealed this law, which negated immigration provisions in the Burlingame Treaty. “Yellow Peril” motivated this legislation, which was passed after increasing immigration of an ethnic group following the 1849 California Gold Rush. For ten points, name this 1882 law that banned citizens from an Asian country from entering the US.",
      "answer": "Chinese Exclusion Act of 1882"
    },
    {
      "question": "Three related men each named Francisco de Montejo conquered this region in the 16th century. A site in this region includes El Castillo, a step-pyramid dedicated to Kukulcan, and a Great Ball Court. One state in this region has capital at Mer´ıda, and cities like Uxmal [oosh-mall] and Chichen Itza are also found in this region. The homeland of the Mayan Civilization was, for ten points, what Mexican peninsula where a meteor impact may have killed the dinosaurs and created the Chicxulub Crater near the Gulf of Mexico?",
      "answer": "Yucatan Peninsula"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1925, this leader put down Sheikh Said’s Islamist Kurdish revolt. This leader hired John Dewey to increase literacy rates by latinizing his country’s alphabet. This man led a national movement that rejected the Treaty of Sevres’ harsh borders and negotiated the Treaty of Lausanne. The “Six Arrows” ideology of secular, democratic reform was developed to replace Ottoman norms by, for ten points, what modernizing first President of Turkey?",
      "answer": [
        "Mustafa Kemal Ataturk",
        "either underlined name"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A socialist politician from this country, Emile Vandervelde, argued against its ruler’s personal ownership of a colony investigated by Roger Casement. This country created the Force Publique, an armed force that cut the hands off of enslaved rubber workers in a colony that the Berlin Conference had given to this country’s King Leopold II. For ten points, name this country that once owned the Congo Free State.",
      "answer": "Belgium"
    },
    {
      "question": "A blindfolded man is tied to a post in a print by this artist titled “Nothing To Be Done,” part of a series called The Disasters of War that shows violent scenes from the Peninsular War. This artist’s painting of Mameluke horsemen in the Puerta del Sol is set one day before another of his works that shows a firing squad aiming at a man in a white shirt outside of Madrid. For ten points, name this Spanish painter of The Third of May, 1808.",
      "answer": "Francisco Goya y Lucientes"
    },
    {
      "question": "The ship Baltic was assigned to bring troops to this location under the command of Gustavus Fox. The first shots fired from this location were overseen by Abner Doubleday, while Robert Anderson commanded its defense. The Star of the West, a civilian ship, tried to resupply this location three months before it was targeted by cannon fire ordered by P.G.T. Beauregard. For ten points, name this Charleston fort, the site of the first battle of the Civil War.",
      "answer": "Fort Sumter"
    },
    {
      "question": "Scipio Aemilianus facilitates dialogue between historical Romans in this author’s On the Commonwealth. This author lays out the foundations for a new Roman constitution is On the Laws, which survives in fragments. After this man’s execution, Fulvia reportedly stabbed his dead tongue with a hairpin to punish him for speaking the Philippics against her husband, Mark Antony. For ten points, name this Roman orator and philosopher who was executed by the Second Triumvirate.",
      "answer": "Marcus Tullius Cicero"
    },
    {
      "question": "This activity was the subject of Lee v. Weisman, a 1992 Supreme Court case decided by Anthony Kennedy’s late change of opinion. In Engel v. Vitale, the Supreme Court ruled it unconstitutional for officials to encourage this activity; in 2000, the Court expanded that ruling to apply to students leading this activity themselves at football games. The Establishment Clause of the First Amendment forbids, for ten points, what type of public religious expression?",
      "answer": "public school prayer"
    },
    {
      "question": "This specific activity was conceived by Benton MacKaye, who opened its first section from Bear Mountain in 1923. A challenging section of this activity is known as the Hundred-Mile Wilderness. Randall Lee Smith murdered two women performing this action in 1981, and Mark Sanford used this activity to cover up his extramarital affair in 2009. For ten points, name this activity whose complete version can be conducted from Mount Katahdin in Maine to Springer Mountain in Georgia.",
      "answer": [
        "hiking the Appalachian Trail",
        "equivalents for hiking, such as walking the Appalachian Trail"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This band, whose members included Roger Taylor and John Deacon, negotiated with the East German government to use footage from Metropolis in the music video for “Radio Ga Ga.” Another song by this band includes the repeated cry “Bismillah!” and opens by asking “Is this the real life? Is this just fantasy?” In 1991, this band’s lead singer died 24 hours after announcing his battle with AIDS. For ten points, name this British rock band fronted by Freddie Mercury whose hits included “Bohemian Rhapsody” and “We Are the Champions.”",
        "answer": "Queen"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The female subject of Queen’s 1974 hit “Killer Queen” is described as “a built-in remedy/for” these two world leaders. One of these two men was killed in 1963; the other was deposed in 1964 and died of a heart attack in 1971.",
        "answer": [
          "Nikita Khrushchev and John F. Kennedy",
          "in either order",
          "prompt if only one is given. Note that “John” isn’t required as part of this answer - unlike most JFK questions - because the lyric is “for Khrushchev and Kennedy.”"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Glen Grey Act was a precursor to this policy, which Daniel Malan campaigned on. The Suppression of Communism Act was used to quell protests against this policy. A militant fighter against this policy gave the “I am prepared to die speech” in the Rivonia Trial. Oliver Tambo led Umkhonto we Sizwe [oom-KON-toe we SEES-way] to fight this policy, which was ended by F. W. de Klerk and Nelson Mandela. For ten points, name this policy of racial segregation policy in South Afirca whose name means “separateness.”",
        "answer": "apartheid"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The militant group Umkhonto we Sizwe, or Spear of the Nation, was created in response to this 1960 massacre of protesters at a police station.",
        "answer": "Sharpeville Massacre"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The perpetrator of this event was severely beaten by John Geary and James Parker, before its victim said “Go easy on him, boys.” George Cortelyou was unable to prevent this event, which took place at the Temple of Music during the Pan-American Exposition. The perpetrator of this crime was radicalized after hearing Emma Goldman deliver a speech on violence, and used a handkerchief to conceal his revolver. For ten points, name this 1901 crime that elevated Teddy Roosevelt to the presidency.",
        "answer": "assassination or murder, shooting, etc. of William McKinley"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This anarchist shot McKinley and, despite Emma Goldman’s appeal for sympathy, was executed for the crime two months later.",
        "answer": "Leon Czolgosz , but be lenient"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These devices, including some installed on Arizona’s Mount Bigelow, were improved after Cold War work on monitoring Soviet satellites inspired the development of adaptive optics. Karl Jansky names a series of 27 of these devices in New Mexico that form a Very Large Array. Isaac Newton invented a form of these devices with reduced aberration; that reflecting type improved on the refracting version, which Galileo used to observe the moons of Jupiter. For ten points, name these astronomical devices.",
        "answer": "telescopes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Very Large Array of telescopes detect signals in this region of the electromagnetic spectrum. This type of wave was first discovered coming from space by Karl Jansky in 1931 at Bell Labs.",
        "answer": "radio waves"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During the third day of this event, James Stockdale commanded a squadron of F-8 fighters, claiming to have “the best seat in the house” for it. The first day of this event involved a DESOTO intelligence missionthatwastrackedbypatrolboats,afterwhichtheTurner Joy joinedforsupport.Afterthisincident involving the USS Maddox, Congress passed a resolution giving President Lyndon Johnson sweeping war powers. For ten points, name this 1964 naval confrontation off the coast of Vietnam.",
        "answer": [
          "Gulf of Tonkin Incident",
          "USS Maddox Incident before “USS Maddox” is read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This longest serving Secretary of Defense urged President Johnson to retaliate after the Gulf of Tonkin Incident.",
        "answer": "Robert Strange McNamara"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer reused a theme from his Gegenliebe in a piece that had to be restarted at its premiere concert, his Choral Fantasy. That concert of this man’s works also featured a five-movement symphony depicting a thunderstorm and a piece whose opening motif was used by the Allies to represent “V for Victory” in World War II. The notes G-G-G-E form the “fate knocking on the door” motif in, for ten points, what German composer’s fifth of nine symphonies?",
        "answer": "Ludwig van Beethoven"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned 1808 concert featured Beethoven as the soloist premiering the fourth of his pieces in what genre? Beethoven wrote five in total, the last of which is nicknamed “Emperor.”",
        "answer": "piano concerto"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "William Alden Smith’s investigation of this event, held in the Waldorf-Astoria hotel, described it as an “act of God.” A stray boat containing the bodies of three victims of this event was discovered a month later by the Oceanic. The Carpathia arrived to rescue survivors of this event, but only one-third of its victims could have found room in a lifeboat. For ten points, name this 1912 disaster in which an “unsinkable ship” sank on its maiden voyage.",
        "answer": "sinking of the RMS Titanic"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Among the Titanic’s victims were its architect, Thomas Andrews, and this man, its captain.",
        "answer": "Edward Smith"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These units fought with allied cavalry that were organized into alae. These army units were divided into smaller units called maniples and organized into three layers based on experience. After twenty five years of service in one of these units, a veteran was granted citizenship. Each possessed an eagle standard and they were organized into ten separate cohorts, each commanded by a centurion. Thousands of men fought in, for ten points, what largest unit of the Roman army?",
        "answer": "legion"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Entry requirements to the legions were relaxed by this Roman general, a six-time consul and uncle of Julius Caesar. Legionnaires were nicknamed his mules because of the heavy packs he made them wear.",
        "answer": "Gaius Marius"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "American Inventions",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Invention whose patent caused a feud between Elisha Grey and Alexander Graham Bell.",
          "answer": "telephone"
        },
        {
          "question": "Navigation system based on a series of over 30 satellites that was developed by the US Air Force.",
          "answer": "GPS or Global Positioning System"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ben Franklin invention that protected buildings from damage during storms.",
          "answer": "lightning rod"
        },
        {
          "question": "Household device made possible by an image dissector developed by Philo Farnsworth.",
          "answer": "television or TV"
        },
        {
          "question": "Inventor of the mechanical reaper who established a manufacturing business in Chicago.",
          "answer": "Cyrus McCormick"
        },
        {
          "question": "Industry that was greatly improved by Norbert Rillieux’s [rill-yoo’s] evaporator, which increased the concentration of cane juice.",
          "answer": [
            "sugar industry",
            "sugarcane"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Four-word phrase transmitted by Samuel Morse from Washington to Baltimore in 1844.",
          "answer": "What hath God wrought?"
        },
        {
          "question": "Proprietor of the Frying Pan Ranch who invented barbed wire.",
          "answer": "Joseph Glidden"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "20th Century European Leaders",
      "prompt": "Given information about a leader, name the country in which...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Prime Minister Aldo Moro was kidnapped, murdered, and abandoned in Rome.",
          "answer": "Italy or Italian Republic"
        },
        {
          "question": "Christian X [the tenth] rode through the streets of Copenhagen during Nazi occupation.",
          "answer": "Denmark"
        },
        {
          "question": "Clement Attlee and the Labour Party created the National Health Service.",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland",
            "UK",
            "Great Britain",
            "England"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Kurt Waldheim was elected President despite lying about his service in the Wehrmacht, which he joined after the Nazis annexed this country.",
          "answer": "Republic of Austria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Erich Honecker advocated “consumer socialism” and Walter Ulbricht’s “New Economic System” ruffled Communist feathers.",
          "answer": "East Germany or the German Democratic Republic"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nicolae Ceausescu [cho-sess-koo] was overthrown in a 1989 revolution.",
          "answer": "Romania"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rysto Ryti led the nation in the Continuation War against the Soviets.",
          "answer": "Republic of Finland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ante Paveli´c [an-tay pah-veh-lich] established the Ustashe regime within Yugoslavia.",
          "answer": "Independent State of Croatia if Yugoslavia is answered before mentioned, prompt and finish reading the part"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Opium Wars",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country that lost both Opium Wars to Britain.",
          "answer": "China"
        },
        {
          "question": "Reigning British queen during the 19th century Opium Wars.",
          "answer": "Victoria"
        },
        {
          "question": "European nation that joined Britain during the Second Opium War after the execution of Auguste Chapdelaine [oh-GOOST shap-deh-LAN].",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty in power during the Opium Wars. It fell during the Xinhai [shin-hai] Revolution of 1911.",
          "answer": "Qing Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where the unequal treaty ending the First Opium War was signed.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Nanjing"
        },
        {
          "question": "Port city where Commissioner Lin destroyed the opium that started the First Opium War.",
          "answer": "Canton or Guangzhou"
        },
        {
          "question": "Waterway, first connected during the Sui Dynasty, that the British blocked during the Opium Wars.",
          "answer": "Grand Canal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Event that sparked the Second Opium War, when officials seized the namesake merchant ship.",
          "answer": "Arrow incident"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) John Bowring signed a treaty with this kingdom to grant Britain most favored nation status. Taksin the Great liberated this nation, which was modernized during the Chakri dynasty by (20 pts)",
        "Mongkut. While it was ruled by King Narai of the Ayutthaya Dynasty, the Taungoo Dynasty of Burma invaded this nation, though this Southeast Asian country was (10 pts)",
        "never colonized by European powers. Several kings named Rama have ruled, for ten points, what country that was once known as Siam and whose capital is Bangkok?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Thailand",
        "Siam before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Aboriginal leader William Cooper led a march in Melbourne protesting this event, one of the few global protests against it. This event followed the announcement that “spontaneous” demonstrations would not be hampered, made by Joseph (20 pts)",
        "Goebbels. Over ten thousand men were taken to Dachau concentration camp after this event, which was a reaction to the death of (10 pts)",
        "diplomat Ernst von Rath. For ten points, name this 1938 event in Nazi Germany in which thousands of Jewish businesses and synagogues were destroyed."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Kristallnacht",
        "Night of Broken Glass"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was advised by the half-French Poker Joe, and despite being previously absent, he led forces to victory at the Battle of White Bird Canyon. After having led his forces hundreds of miles from his native Wallowa Valley, this leader was finally defeated by (20 pts)",
        "Oliver Howard at the Battle of Bear Paw. After this man’s 1877 surrender to Nelson Miles, he declared “From where the (10 pts)",
        "sun now stands, I will fight no more forever.” For ten points, name this Nez Perce chief who fiercely resisted attempts at relocation."
      ],
      "answer": "Chief Joseph"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A lecture by this author subtitled “The Monsters and the Critics” argued that Beowulf should be studied as a poem, not as a pseudo-historical work. C.S. Lewis and this writer were leading members of the (20 pts)",
        "Inklings, an Oxford literary group. A set of three jewels that are infused with the essence of two trees provide the title of a book by this man that was compiled by his son (10 pts)",
        "Christopher, The Silmarillion. For ten points, name this author who created Middle Earth in his Lord of the Rings trilogy."
      ],
      "answer": "J.R.R. Tolkien or John Ronald Reuel Tolkien"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this conflict, a navy delayed their retreat because of a lunar eclipse; that decision by Nicias doomed the entire force. After Callicratidas lost at this war’s Battle of Arginusae [ar-jin-oo-say], (20 pts)",
        "Lysander retook command and won at Aegospotami. Alcibiades [al- si-BYE-uh-dees] defected from one side in this war shortly before the disastrous Sicilian Expedition, then later re-defected to (10 pts)",
        "Athens. Thucydides wrote a History of, for ten points, what 5th century BC war that Athens lost to Sparta, named for a Greek peninsula?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Peloponnesian War",
        "Sicilian Expedition until “Callicratidas” is read, then prompt on it until it is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) As Chair of the Senate Judiciary Committee, this man prevented witnesses from testifying on Anita Hill’s behalf during Clarence Thomas’s Supreme Court nomination hearings. In 2006, this politician controversially claimed you needed a “slight Indian accent” to go to a (20 pts)",
        "7/11 in his state. This man introduced harsh mandatory minimums in the 1994 Crime Bill, which he wrote during his fourth term as Senator. The Presidential (10 pts)",
        "Medal of Freedom was given in January 2017 to, for ten points, what Delaware politician who declined to run for President in 2016 after serving as Barack Obama’s Vice President?"
      ],
      "answer": "Joseph “Joe” Biden Jr."
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one election, this politician considered Colonel Sanders as his running mate before settling on Curtis LeMay for his American Independent Party ticket. Four years later, while this man was campaigning at the Laurel Shopping Center, he (20 pts)",
        "survived an assassination attempt by Arthur Bremer. Vivian Malone and James Hood were harassed by this man’s (10 pts)",
        "“Stand in the Schoolhouse Door,” and he announced “segregation now, segregation tomorrow, segregation forever” in a 1963 speech. For ten points, name this former governor of Alabama."
      ],
      "answer": "George Corley Wallace Jr."
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city’s Al-Azhar Mosque is a leading world center of Sunni Islam, and its Ben Ezra Synagogue was found to hold over 300,000 Jewish manuscript fragments in the 19th century. This city is the official home of (20 pts)",
        "Tawadros II, the Pope of the Coptic Orthodox Church. In 2011, Muslims and Christians protested together in this city’s (10 pts)",
        "Tahrir Square on “Martyr’s Sunday” against the government of Hosni Mubarak. For ten points, name this largest Middle Eastern city, the capital of Egypt."
      ],
      "answer": "Cairo"
    }
  ]
}